<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linear_models on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</title>
    <link>https://www.statforbiology.com/tags/linear_models/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linear_models on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2018, @AndreaOnofri</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.statforbiology.com/tags/linear_models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Stabilising transformations: how do I present my results?</title>
      <link>https://www.statforbiology.com/2019/stat_general_reportingresults/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.statforbiology.com/2019/stat_general_reportingresults/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;ANOVA is routinely used in applied biology for data analyses, although, in some instances, the basic assumptions of normality and homoscedasticity of residuals do not hold. In those instances, most biologists would be inclined to adopt some sort of stabilising transformations (logarithm, square root, arcsin square root…), prior to ANOVA. Yes, there might be more advanced and elegant solutions, but stabilising transformations are suggested in most traditional biometry books, they are very straightforward to apply and they do not require any specific statistical software. I do not think that this traditional technique should be underrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the use of stabilising transformations has one remarkable drawback, it may hinder the clarity of results. I’d like to give a simple, but relevant example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;an-example-with-counts&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;An example with counts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the following dataset, that represents the counts of insects on 15 independent leaves, treated with the insecticides A, B and C (5 replicates):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dataset &amp;lt;- structure(data.frame(
  Insecticide = structure(c(1L, 1L, 1L, 1L, 1L, 
    2L, 2L, 2L, 2L, 2L, 3L, 3L, 3L, 3L, 3L), 
    .Label = c(&amp;quot;A&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;B&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;), class = &amp;quot;factor&amp;quot;), 
  Count = c(448, 906, 484, 477, 634, 211, 276, 
    415, 587, 298, 50, 90, 73, 44, 26)), 
  .Names = c(&amp;quot;Insecticide&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Count&amp;quot;))
dataset
##    Insecticide Count
## 1            A   448
## 2            A   906
## 3            A   484
## 4            A   477
## 5            A   634
## 6            B   211
## 7            B   276
## 8            B   415
## 9            B   587
## 10           B   298
## 11           C    50
## 12           C    90
## 13           C    73
## 14           C    44
## 15           C    26&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should not expect that a count variable is normally distributed with equal variances. Indeed, a graph of residuals against expected values shows clear signs of heteroscedasticity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mod &amp;lt;- lm(Count ~ Insecticide, data=dataset)
plot(mod, which = 1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.statforbiology.com/post/Stat_General_reportingResults_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-2-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this situation, a logarithmic transformation is often suggested to produce a new normal and homoscedastic dataset. Therefore we take the log-transformed variable and submit it to ANOVA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;model &amp;lt;- lm(log(Count) ~ Insecticide, data=dataset)
print(anova(model), digits=6)
## Analysis of Variance Table
## 
## Response: log(Count)
##             Df   Sum Sq Mean Sq F value     Pr(&amp;gt;F)    
## Insecticide  2 15.82001 7.91000 50.1224 1.4931e-06 ***
## Residuals   12  1.89376 0.15781                       
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1
summary(model)
## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = log(Count) ~ Insecticide, data = dataset)
## 
## Residuals:
##     Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max 
## -0.6908 -0.1849 -0.1174  0.2777  0.5605 
## 
## Coefficients:
##              Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)    
## (Intercept)    6.3431     0.1777  35.704 1.49e-13 ***
## InsecticideB  -0.5286     0.2512  -2.104   0.0572 .  
## InsecticideC  -2.3942     0.2512  -9.529 6.02e-07 ***
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1
## 
## Residual standard error: 0.3973 on 12 degrees of freedom
## Multiple R-squared:  0.8931, Adjusted R-squared:  0.8753 
## F-statistic: 50.12 on 2 and 12 DF,  p-value: 1.493e-06&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example, the standard error for each mean (SEM) corresponds to &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sqrt{0.158/5}\)&lt;/span&gt;. In the end, we might show the following table of means for transformed data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- table --&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Insecticide&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Means (log n.)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;6.343&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;5.815&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;3.985&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;SEM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;0.178&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;!-- table --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we loose clarity: how many insects did we have on each leaf? If we present in our manuscript a table like this one we might be asked by our readers or by the reviewer to report the means on the original measurement unit. What should we do, then? Here are some suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can present the means of the original data with standard deviations. This is clearly less than optimal, if we want to suggest more than the bare variability of the observed sample. Furthermore, &lt;strong&gt;please remember that the means of original data may not be a good measure of central tendency, if the original population is strongly ‘asymmetric’ (skewed)!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can show back-transformed means. Accordingly, if we have done, e.g., a logarithmic transformation, we can exponentiate the means of transformed data and report them back to the original measurement unit. Back-transformed means ‘estimate’ the medians of the original populations, which may be regarded as better measures of central tendency for skewed data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We suggest that the use of the second method. However, this leaves us with the problem of adding a measure of uncertainty to back-transformed means. No worries, we can use the delta method to back-transform standard errors. It is straightforward:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;take the first derivative of the back-transform function [in this case the first derivative of exp(X)=exp(X)] and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;multiply it by the standard error of the transformed data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may be simply done by hand, with e.g &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(exp(6.343) \times 0.178 = 101.19\)&lt;/span&gt; (for insecticide A). This ‘manual’ solution is always available, regardless of the statistical software at hand. With R, we can use the ‘emmeans’ package (Lenth, 2016):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(emmeans)
countM &amp;lt;- emmeans(model, ~Insecticide, transform = &amp;quot;response&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is enough to set the argument ‘transform’ to ’response, although the transformation must be embedded in the model. It means: it is ok if we coded the model as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;log(Count) ~ Insecticide&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, it fails if we coded the model as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;logCount ~ Insecticide&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where the transformation was performed prior to fitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the back-transformed standard error is different for each mean (there is no homogeneity of variances on the original scale, but we knew this already). Back-transformed data might be presented as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Insecticide&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;Mean&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;SE&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;568.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;101.19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;335.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;59.68&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;51.88&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;9.57&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be appropriate to state it clearly (e.g. in a footnote), that means and SEs were obtained by back-transformation via the delta method. Far clearer, isn’t it? As I said, there are other solutions, such as fitting a GLM, but stabilising transformations are simple and they are easily acceptable in biological Journals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to know something more about the delta-method you might start from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.statforbiology.com/2019/stat_general_thedeltamethod/&#34;&gt;my post here&lt;/a&gt;. A few years ago, some collegues and I have also discussed these issues in a journal paper (Onofri et al., 2010).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrea Onofri&lt;br /&gt;
University of Perugia (Italy)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lenth, R.V., 2016. Least-Squares Means: The R Package lsmeans. Journal of Statistical Software 69. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v069.i01&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v069.i01&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Onofri, A., Carbonell, E.A., Piepho, H.-P., Mortimer, A.M., Cousens, R.D., 2010. Current statistical issues in Weed Research. Weed Research 50, 5–24.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do we combine errors? The linear case</title>
      <link>https://www.statforbiology.com/2019/stat_general_errorpropagation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.statforbiology.com/2019/stat_general_errorpropagation/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;In our research work, we usually fit models to experimental data. Our aim is to estimate some biologically relevant parameters, together with their standard errors. Very often, these parameters are interesting in themselves, as they represent means, differences, rates or other important descriptors. In other cases, we use those estimates to derive further indices, by way of some appropriate calculations. For example, think that we have two parameter estimates, say Q and W, with standard errors respectively equal to &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_Q\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_W\)&lt;/span&gt;: it might be relevant to calculate the amount:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[Z = AQ + BW + C\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where A, B and C are three coefficients. The above operation is named ‘linear combination’; it is a sort of a weighted sum of model parameters. The question is: what is the standard error of Z? I would like to show this by way of a simple biological example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;example&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Example&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have measured the germination rate for seeds of &lt;em&gt;Brassica rapa&lt;/em&gt; at six levels of water potential in the substrate (-1, -0.9, -0.8, -0.7, -0.6 and -0.5 MPa). We would like to predict the germination rate for a water potential level of -0.75 MPa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literature references suggest that the relationship between germination rate and water potential in the substrate is linear. Therefore, as the first step, we fit a linear regression model to our observed data. If we are into R, the code to accomplish this task is shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;GR &amp;lt;- c(0.11, 0.20, 0.34, 0.46, 0.56, 0.68)
Psi &amp;lt;- c(-1, -0.9, -0.8, -0.7, -0.6, -0.5)
lMod &amp;lt;- lm(GR ~ Psi)
summary(lMod)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
## Call:
## lm(formula = GR ~ Psi)
## 
## Residuals:
##          1          2          3          4          5          6 
##  0.0076190 -0.0180952  0.0061905  0.0104762 -0.0052381 -0.0009524 
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)    
## (Intercept)  1.25952    0.02179   57.79 5.37e-07 ***
## Psi          1.15714    0.02833   40.84 2.15e-06 ***
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1
## 
## Residual standard error: 0.01185 on 4 degrees of freedom
## Multiple R-squared:  0.9976, Adjusted R-squared:  0.997 
## F-statistic:  1668 on 1 and 4 DF,  p-value: 2.148e-06&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is clear that we can use the fitted model to calculate the GR-value at -0.75 MPa, as &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(GR = 1.26 - 1.16 \times 0.75 = 0.39\)&lt;/span&gt;. This is indeed a linear combination of model parameters, as we have shown above. Q and W are the estimated model parameters, while &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(A = 1\)&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(B = -0.75\)&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(C = 0\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the derived response is also an estimate and we need to give a measure of uncertainty. For both model parameters we have standard errors; the question is: how does the uncertainty in parameter estimates propagates to their linear combination? In simpler words: it is easy to build a weightes sum of model parameters, but, how do we make a weighted sum of their standard errors?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sokal and Rohlf (1981) at pag. 818 of their book, show that, in general, it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ \textrm{var}(A \, Q + B \, W) = A^2 \sigma^2_Q + B^2 \sigma^2_W + 2AB \sigma_{QW} \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(\sigma_{QW}\)&lt;/span&gt; is the covariance of Q and W. I attach the proof below; it is pretty simple to understand and it is worth the effort. However, several students in biology are rather reluctant when they have to delve into maths. Therefore, I would also like to give an empirical ‘proof’, by using some simple R code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s take two samples (Q and W) and combine them by using two coefficients A and B. Let’s calculate the variance for the combination:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Q &amp;lt;- c(12, 14, 11, 9)
W &amp;lt;- c(2, 4, 7, 8)
A &amp;lt;- 2
B &amp;lt;- 3
C &amp;lt;- 4
var(A * Q + B * W + C)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 35.58333&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A^2 * var(Q) + B^2 * var(W) + 2 * A * B * cov(Q, W)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 35.58333&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see that the results match exactly! In our example, the variance and covariance of estimates are retrieved by using the ‘vcov()’ function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vcov(lMod)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##              (Intercept)          Psi
## (Intercept) 0.0004749433 0.0006020408
## Psi         0.0006020408 0.0008027211&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sigma2Q &amp;lt;- vcov(lMod)[1,1]
sigma2W &amp;lt;- vcov(lMod)[2,2]
sigmaQW &amp;lt;- vcov(lMod)[1,2]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard error for the prediction is simply obtained as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sqrt( sigma2Q + 0.75^2 * sigma2W - 2 * 0.75 * sigmaQW )&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## [1] 0.004838667&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-functions-predict-and-glht&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The functions ‘predict()’ and ‘glht()’&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have understood the concept, we can use R to make the calculations. For this example, the ‘predict()’ method represents the most logical approach. We only need to pass the model object and the X value which we have to make a prediction for. This latter value needs to be organised as a data frame, with column name(s) matching the name(s) of the X-variable(s) in the original dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;predict(lMod, newdata = data.frame(Psi = -0.75), 
        se.fit = T)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## $fit
##         1 
## 0.3916667 
## 
## $se.fit
## [1] 0.004838667
## 
## $df
## [1] 4
## 
## $residual.scale
## [1] 0.01185227&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the predict method, there is another function of more general interest, which can be used to build linear combinations of model parameters. It is the ‘glht()’ function in the ‘multcomp’ package. To use this function, we need a model object and we need to organise the coefficients for the transformation in a matrix, with as many rows as there are combinations to calculate. When writing the coefficients, we disregard C: we have seen that every constant value does not affect the variance of the transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, just imagine that we want to predict the GR for two levels of water potential, i.e. -0.75 (as above) and -0.55 MPa. The coefficients (A, B) for the combinations are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Z1 &amp;lt;- c(1, -0.75)
Z2 &amp;lt;- c(1, -0.55)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We pile up the two vectors in one matrix with two rows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;M &amp;lt;- matrix(c(Z1, Z2), 2, 2, byrow = T)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now we pass that matrix to the ‘glht()’ function as an argument:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(multcomp)
lcombs &amp;lt;- glht(lMod, linfct = M, adjust = &amp;quot;none&amp;quot;)
summary(lcombs)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## 
##   Simultaneous Tests for General Linear Hypotheses
## 
## Fit: lm(formula = GR ~ Psi)
## 
## Linear Hypotheses:
##        Estimate Std. Error t value Pr(&amp;gt;|t|)    
## 1 == 0 0.391667   0.004839   80.94 2.30e-07 ***
## 2 == 0 0.623095   0.007451   83.62 2.02e-07 ***
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 &amp;#39;***&amp;#39; 0.001 &amp;#39;**&amp;#39; 0.01 &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; 0.05 &amp;#39;.&amp;#39; 0.1 &amp;#39; &amp;#39; 1
## (Adjusted p values reported -- single-step method)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above method can be easily extended to other types of linear models and linear combinations of model parameters. The ‘adjust’ argument is useful whenever we want to obtain familywise confidence intervals, which can account for the multiplicity problem. But this is another story…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy work with these functions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;appendix&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Appendix&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that the variance for a random variable is defined as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ var(Z) = \frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left(Z - \hat{Z}\right)^2 = \\ = \frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left(Z - \frac{1}{n} \sum{Z}\right)^2\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(Z = AQ + BW + C\)&lt;/span&gt;, where A, B and C are the coefficients and Q and W are two random variables, we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ var(Z) = \frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left[AQ + BW + C - \frac{1}{n} \sum{ \left(AQ + BW + C\right)}\right]^2 = \\ 
= \frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left[AQ + BW + C - \frac{1}{n} \sum{ AQ} - \frac{1}{n} \sum{ BW} - \frac{1}{n} \sum{ C}\right]^2 = \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[= \frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left[AQ + BW + C - A \hat{Q} - B \hat{W} - C \right]^2 = \\
= \frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left[\left( AQ - A \hat{Q}\right) + \left( BW - B \hat{W}\right) \right]^2 = \]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ =\frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left[A \left( Q - \hat{Q}\right) + B \left( W - \hat{W}\right) \right]^2 = \\
= \frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left[A^2 \left( Q - \hat{Q}\right)^2 + B^2 \left( W - \hat{W}\right)^2 + 2AB \left( Q - \hat{Q}\right) \left( W - \hat{W}\right)\right] =\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ = A^2 \frac{1}{n-1} \sum{\left( Q - \hat{Q}\right)^2} + B^2 \frac{1}{n-1}\sum \left( W - \hat{W}\right)^2 + 2AB \frac{1}{n-1}\sum{\left[\left( Q - \hat{Q}\right) \left( W - \hat{W}\right)\right]}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;math display&#34;&gt;\[ \textrm{var}(Z) = A^2 \sigma^2_Q + B^2 \sigma^2_W + 2AB \sigma_{Q,W}\]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>