<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2018, @AndreaOnofri</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My first experience with blogdown</title>
      <link>/2018/2018-11_15-first-day-with-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/2018-11_15-first-day-with-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>This is my first day at work with blogdown. I must admit it is pretty overwhelming at the beginning &amp;hellip;
I thought that it might be useful to write down a few notes, to summarise my steps ahead, during the learning process. I do not work with blogdown everyday and I tend to forget things quite easily. Therefore, these notes may help me recap how far I have come. And they might also help other beginners, to speed up their initial steps with such a powerful blogging platform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is R dangerous? Side effects of free software for biologists</title>
      <link>/2014/2014-06-08-the-danger-of-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/2014-06-08-the-danger-of-r/</guid>
      <description>When I started my career in the biological field (it’s already 25 years ago), only the luckiest of us had access to very advanced statistical software. Licenses were very expensive and it was not easy to convince the boss that they were really necessary: “Why do you need to spend so much money to perform an ANOVA?”. Indeed, simple one-way or two-ways ANOVAs were quite easy to perform and one of the people in my group had already built the appropriate routines for several designs, by using the GW-BASIC language.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>