<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blogdown on Fixing the bridge between biologists and statisticians</title>
    <link>https://www.statforbiology.com/tags/blogdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in blogdown on Fixing the bridge between biologists and statisticians</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2023, @AndreaOnofri</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.statforbiology.com/tags/blogdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My first experience with blogdown</title>
      <link>https://www.statforbiology.com/2018/2018-11_15-first-day-with-blogdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.statforbiology.com/2018/2018-11_15-first-day-with-blogdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my first day at work with blogdown. I must admit it is pretty overwhelming at the beginning &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that it might be useful to write down a few notes, to summarise my steps ahead, during the learning process. I do not work with blogdown everyday and I tend to forget things quite easily. Therefore, these notes may help me recap how far I have come. And they might also help other beginners, to speed up their initial steps with such a powerful blogging platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll find my notes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.statforbiology.com/articles/blogdownSteps/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;; I&amp;rsquo;ll try to keep them updated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My learning path with blogdown</title>
      <link>https://www.statforbiology.com/articles/blogdownsteps/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.statforbiology.com/articles/blogdownsteps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my first day at work with blogdown. I must admit it is pretty overwhelming at the beginning &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with R Studio and installed the library &amp;lsquo;blogdown&amp;rsquo;. I followed the instructions and used the &amp;lsquo;NEW PROJECT&amp;rsquo; menu and added a &amp;lsquo;NEW BLOGDOWN SITE&amp;rsquo; to my file system. I selected the &amp;lsquo;hugo-blog-jeffprod&amp;rsquo; theme. This created a bunch of directories in my working directory. If I use the &amp;lsquo;serve_site()&amp;rsquo; function in console, the Hugo server is called and the site is continuously updated, as soon as I make changes and save them. When the server is started, a message appears, saying: &amp;ldquo;Serving the directory PROJECTDIR at http://127.0.0.1:7958&amp;rdquo;. I copied the http address on Safari (I am working on Mac OS&amp;hellip;), so that I can check my changes there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are my steps to the learning the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-1---the-mathjax-problem&#34;&gt;STEP 1 - The MathJax problem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added a post to the &amp;lsquo;content&amp;rsquo; directory. This was a trial post, with an equation in latex code. I immediately noted that there was no support to MathJax. Surfing the net, I found a solution for this. These were my steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The folder &amp;lsquo;themes/hugo-blog-jeffprod/layouts/partials&amp;rsquo; contains the template file &amp;lsquo;header.html&amp;rsquo;. The blogdown documentation suggests not to directly modify this file. Thus I created a copy on the &amp;lsquo;layouts/partials/&amp;rsquo; folder in my root directory. This folder did not exist at the beginning, so I created it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I opened the newly created file &amp;lsquo;layouts/partials/header.html&amp;rsquo; and added the following lines within the &lt;head&gt; &amp;hellip; &lt;/head&gt; section:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;
  src=&amp;quot;https://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Equations seem to render ok, now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-2---change-the-blog-name-and-author&#34;&gt;STEP 2 - Change the blog name and author&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I modified the &amp;lsquo;config.toml&amp;rsquo; file in the root directory and added name and author of the site. An easy step&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-3---clean-the-example-files&#34;&gt;STEP 3 - Clean the example files&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a lot of example posts in the &amp;lsquo;content&amp;rsquo; directory. I removed them all, with no problems. I also had to remove the content of the &amp;lsquo;static&amp;rsquo; folder. These files were not needed, because they belonged to the example posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-4---where-do-i-put-my-post&#34;&gt;Step 4 - Where do I put my post?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New posts need to be put in the &amp;lsquo;content/post&amp;rsquo; directory. In order to add a post, I am using the function &amp;lsquo;blogdown:::new_post_addin()&amp;rsquo; (I like working in console&amp;hellip;), which creates a correct skeleton. Blog posts are listed under the home page of my blog, sorted by date and by tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-5---where-do-i-put-my-non-post-pages&#34;&gt;Step 5 - Where do I put my non-post pages?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not intend to create a pure blog. I wanted also to add static pages, such as articles, tutorials, a project page, links and other stuff. I noted that, when .md or .Rmd files are left in the &amp;lsquo;content&amp;rsquo; folder, a folder with the same name is created in &amp;lsquo;public&amp;rsquo; and the post is rendered within that folder. Therefore, I put a &amp;lsquo;links.md&amp;rsquo; file in the &amp;lsquo;content&amp;rsquo; folder, containing a few links to other web pages of interest. This file is not rendered as a post and it is not visible in my home page. However, a folder named &amp;lsquo;link&amp;rsquo; is created in the public directory, containing the &amp;lsquo;links.md&amp;rsquo; file, rendered as &amp;lsquo;index.html&amp;rsquo; file. Therefore, I can link this file by using the &amp;lsquo;/link/&amp;rsquo; address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-6---how-do-i-create-further-entries-for-the-navigation-bar&#34;&gt;Step 6 - How do I create further entries for the navigation bar?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just created the &amp;lsquo;/link/index.html&amp;rsquo; file in the &amp;lsquo;public&amp;rsquo; directory. I would like the reader to access this web page by clicking on an appropriate link at the top of the home-page, next to the &amp;lsquo;Home&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;About me&amp;rsquo; links. In order to add this link, I had to edit again the &amp;lsquo;layouts/partials/header.html&amp;rsquo; file. In the &amp;lsquo;nav&amp;rsquo; section, there was the line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a class=&amp;quot;navbar-item&amp;quot; href=&amp;quot;{{ &amp;quot;about&amp;quot; | absURL }}&amp;quot;&amp;gt;About me&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This line creates the &amp;lsquo;About me&amp;rsquo; link on the navigation bar. Below this line, I added another line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a class=&amp;quot;navbar-item&amp;quot; href=&amp;quot;{{ &amp;quot;links&amp;quot; | absURL }}&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Links&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;I guess I can use this approach to redirect readers to other web pages of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-7---i-need-to-put-some-order-in-the-content-folder-412019&#34;&gt;Step 7 - I need to put some order in the &amp;lsquo;content&amp;rsquo; folder&#39; (4/1/2019)!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After adding a few non-post pages to my content folder I wanted to avoid too much confusion. I discovered that I can add folders to the &amp;lsquo;content&amp;rsquo; folder. They are rendered as such in the public directory. For example, I created an &amp;lsquo;article&amp;rsquo; folder and put a &amp;lsquo;page1.md&amp;rsquo; file inside it. After rendering, a folder &amp;lsquo;article/page1/&amp;rsquo; is created in the &amp;lsquo;public&amp;rsquo; folder, containing the &amp;lsquo;index.html&amp;rsquo; page, which is the rendered version of the &amp;lsquo;page1.md&amp;rsquo; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I start feeling slightly more confident with blogdown!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-8---literature-support-712019&#34;&gt;Step 8 - Literature support (7/1/2019)!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem took me a while to solve. Lately, I discovered that, in order to be able to insert citations, the post file needs to be &amp;lsquo;.Rmd&amp;rsquo; and not &amp;lsquo;.md.&amp;rsquo; Furthermore, the literature file (&#39;.bib&#39;) and the &amp;lsquo;.csl&amp;rsquo; file need to be in the &amp;lsquo;/content/&amp;rsquo; folder. A reference to both files need to be put in the YAML header, e.g., :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bibliography: myFile.bib
csl: myStyle.csl
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-9---google-analytics-622019&#34;&gt;Step 9 - Google Analytics (6/2/2019)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to track the visits I receive. To do so I enabled Google Analytics and got my tracking id (&lt;a href=&#34;https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/1008080&#34;&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;). I also worked on my &amp;lsquo;config.toml&amp;rsquo; file and added the following statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;GoogleAnalytics = &amp;quot;UA-my_ID&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast to what I expected, Google Analytics did not work and no hits were recorded for my blog. Lately, I worked on the &amp;lsquo;layouts/partials/header.html&amp;rsquo; and added the following code, right after the &amp;lsquo;&lt;head&gt;&amp;rsquo; tag (just replaced &amp;lsquo;UA-my_ID&amp;rsquo; with my tracking id).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;!-- Global Site Tag (gtag.js) - Google Analytics --&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script async src=&amp;quot;https://www.googletagmanager.com/gtag/js?id=UA-my_ID&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
  window.dataLayer = window.dataLayer || [];
  function gtag(){dataLayer.push(arguments);}
  gtag(&#39;js&#39;, new Date());

  gtag(&#39;config&#39;, &#39;UA-my_ID&#39;);
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now Google Analytics works ok!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-10---add-an-rss-template&#34;&gt;Step 10 - Add an RSS Template&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted my RSS feed to contain the whole post and not only a description. I did the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Took the default template from  &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/templates/rss/#the-embedded-rss-xml&#34;&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replaced &amp;lsquo;{{ .Summary | html }}&amp;rsquo; with &amp;lsquo;{{ .Content | html }}&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saved the file as &amp;lsquo;RSS.xml&amp;rsquo;under the &amp;lsquo;layouts&amp;rsquo; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-11---further-info-on-google-analytics-10122020&#34;&gt;Step 11 - Further info on Google Analytics (10/12/2020)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very kind reader (Emma) emailed me that there have been some relevant updates for Google analytics (v4). She pointed me to the following guide: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.websiteplanet.com/blog/ultimate-beginners-guide-google-analytics/&#34;&gt;https://www.websiteplanet.com/blog/ultimate-beginners-guide-google-analytics/&lt;/a&gt;. This is useful, to have a better comprehension of the whole Google Analytics platform, just in case someone is interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-12---adding-an-image-to-a-blog-post-19102021&#34;&gt;Step 12 - Adding an image to a blog post (19/10/2021)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me awhile to figure out how to include a figure in a blog post. Lately I also discovered that there is a blogdown add-in to help with this job (&lt;a href=&#34;https://lcolladotor.github.io/2018/03/07/blogdown-insert-image-addin/#.YW8HJC8RpTY&#34;&gt;see this post here&lt;/a&gt;), but I wanted to master the whole process. I solved the problem like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;created an &amp;lsquo;img&amp;rsquo; folder within the &amp;lsquo;static&amp;rsquo; folder in my blogdown project directory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put all the images I wanted to include in blog posts in that folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the markdown code:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;![caption](/img/figFileName.png)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be careful: the &amp;lsquo;slash&amp;rsquo; character at the beginning of file path is fundamental, otherwise the code does not work. Of course, you can use html tags to center your figure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;p style=&amp;quot;text-align:center&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
![](/_Figures/Stat_drcte_3-method-data.png){width=90%}
&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;step-13---changing-the-title-of-the-home-page-14122023&#34;&gt;Step 13 - Changing the title of the home page (14/12/2023)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem stupid, but it took me awhile to figure out how I could possibly change the title for the homepage. Lately, in the cointent folder I discovered a file named &amp;lsquo;_index.Rmarkdown&amp;rsquo;, containing only the YAML header with&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
title: Homepage title
---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is where the homepage title is defined. As far as I could see, all other test in the body of this file is neglected.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>