<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2021 on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</title>
    <link>/archives/2021/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2021 on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2018, @AndreaOnofri</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/archives/2021/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>lmDiallel: a new R package to fit diallel models. The Griffing&#39;s models (1956)</title>
      <link>/2021/stat_met_diallel_griffing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/stat_met_diallel_griffing/</guid>
      <description>Diallel mating designs are often used by plant breeders to compare the possible crosses between a set of genotypes. In spite of such widespread usage, the process of data analysis in R is not yet strightforward and it is not clear which tool should be routinely used. We recently gave a small contribution by publishing a paper in Plant Breeding (Onofri et al., 2020 ), where we advocated the idea that models for diallel crosses are just a class of general linear models, that should be fit by Ordinary Least Squares (OLS) or REstricted Maximum Likelihood methods (REML).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lmDiallel: a new R package to fit diallel models. The Hayman&#39;s model (type 2)</title>
      <link>/2021/stat_met_diallel_hayman2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/stat_met_diallel_hayman2/</guid>
      <description>This posts follows two other previously published posts, where we presented our new ‘lmDiallel’ package (see here) and showed how we can use it to fit the Hayman’s model type 1, as proposed in Hayman (1954) (see here). In this post, we will give a further example relating to another very widespread model from the same author, the Hayman’s model type 2. We apologise for some overlapping with previous posts: we think this is necessary so that each post can be read on its own.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>