<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2021 on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</title>
    <link>/archives/2021/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2021 on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2018, @AndreaOnofri</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/archives/2021/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Split-plot designs: the transition to mixed models for a dinosaur</title>
      <link>/2021/stat_lmm_splitplottransition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/stat_lmm_splitplottransition/</guid>
      <description>Those who long ago took courses in ‘analysis of variance’ or ‘experimental design’ … would have learned methods … based on observed and expected mean squares and methods of testing based on ‘error strata’ (if you weren’t forced to learn this, consider yourself lucky). (Douglas Bates, 2006).
In a previous post, I already mentioned that, due to my age, I see myself as a dinosaur within the R-users community. I already mentioned how difficult it is, for a dinosaur, to adjust to new concepts and paradigms in data analysis, after having done things differently for a long time ( see this post here ).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pairwise comparisons in nonlinear regression</title>
      <link>/2021/stat_nls_paircomp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/stat_nls_paircomp/</guid>
      <description>Pairwise comparisons are one of the most debated topic in agricultural research: they are very often used and, sometimes, abused, in literature. I have nothing against the appropriate use of this very useful technique and, for those who are interested, some colleagues and I have given a bunch of (hopefully) useful suggestions in a paper, a few years ago (follow this link here).
Pairwise comparisons usually follow the application of some sort of linear or generalised linear model; in this setting, the ‘emmeans’ package (Lenth, 2020) is very handy, as it uses a very logical approach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lmDiallel: a new R package to fit diallel models. The Griffing&#39;s models (1956)</title>
      <link>/2021/stat_met_diallel_griffing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/stat_met_diallel_griffing/</guid>
      <description>Diallel mating designs are often used by plant breeders to compare the possible crosses between a set of genotypes. In spite of such widespread usage, the process of data analysis in R is not yet strightforward and it is not clear which tool should be routinely used. We recently gave a small contribution by publishing a paper in Plant Breeding (Onofri et al., 2020 ), where we advocated the idea that models for diallel crosses are just a class of general linear models, that should be fit by Ordinary Least Squares (OLS) or REstricted Maximum Likelihood methods (REML).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lmDiallel: a new R package to fit diallel models. The Hayman&#39;s model (type 2)</title>
      <link>/2021/stat_met_diallel_hayman2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/stat_met_diallel_hayman2/</guid>
      <description>This posts follows two other previously published posts, where we presented our new ‘lmDiallel’ package (see here) and showed how we can use it to fit the Hayman’s model type 1, as proposed in Hayman (1954) (see here). In this post, we will give a further example relating to another very widespread model from the same author, the Hayman’s model type 2. We apologise for some overlapping with previous posts: we think this is necessary so that each post can be read on its own.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>