<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2020 on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</title>
    <link>/archives/2020/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2020 on The broken bridge between biologists and statisticians</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2018, @AndreaOnofri</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/archives/2020/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A collection of self-starters for nonlinear regression in R</title>
      <link>/2020/stat_nls_usefulfunctions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/stat_nls_usefulfunctions/</guid>
      <description>Usually, the first step of every nonlinear regression analysis is to select the function \(f\), which best describes the phenomenon under study. The next step is to fit this function to the observed data, possibly by using some sort of nonlinear least squares algorithms. These algorithms are iterative, in the sense that they start from some initial values of model parameters and repeat a sequence of operations, which continuously improve the initial guesses, until the least squares solution is approximately reached.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-starting routines for nonlinear regression models</title>
      <link>/2020/stat_nls_selfstarting/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/stat_nls_selfstarting/</guid>
      <description>In R, the drc package represents one of the main solutions for nonlinear regression and dose-response analyses (Ritz et al., 2015). It comes with a lot of nonlinear models, which are useful to describe several biological processes, from plant growth to bioassays, from herbicide degradation to seed germination. These models are provided with self-starting functions, which free the user from the hassle of providing initial guesses for model parameters. Indeed, getting these guesses may be a tricky task, both for students and for practitioners.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear combinations of model parameters in regression</title>
      <link>/2020/stat_nls_gnlht/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/stat_nls_gnlht/</guid>
      <description>Nonlinear regression plays an important role in my research and teaching activities. While I often use the ‘drm()’ function in the ‘drc’ package for my research work, I tend to prefer the ‘nls()’ function for teaching purposes, mainly because, in my opinion, the transition from linear models to nonlinear models is smoother, for beginners. One problem with ‘nls()’ is that, in contrast to ‘drm()’, it is not specifically tailored to the needs of biologists or students in biology.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>